in this video we're going to work on
some basic problems associated with
mechanical waves
so here we have a graphical
representation of a wave
what is the amplitude and wavelength of
the wave shown below
the amplitude is the distance between
the midpoint and the highest point of
the wave
so it's from zero to three so in this
example the amplitude is three meters
now to find a wavelength you could find
the distance
between the crests of the wave
or the distance between the troughs
or
you could find
the distance that it takes to complete
one cycle so from here
to here
so how many cycles do we have in this
wave
so this is one complete cycle
that's two cycles
and that's three cycles
so in three cycles the wave traveled a
distance of 10 meters
so we got to find the distance it
travels in one cycle
so that's going to be 10 meters
divided by 3. so the wavelength is going
to be 3.33 meters
so this position is about 3.33
and then here it's 6.67 and then it's
going to be 10 meters
number two
determine the amplitude period and
frequency
of the mechanical wave shown below
so feel free to try this if you want to
so the amplitude is the distance between
the midpoint or the center line
and the crest of the wave so in this
example we can clearly see that it's 10
meters
so it's basically equal to that number
now what about the period and the
frequency of the wave
the period is the time it takes to make
one complete cycle
so notice that the five seconds
corresponds to the first quarter of the
cycle
so at the second quarter which is here
it's going to be 10 seconds
at the third quarter it's 15 seconds
and at the full cycle at the end of it
it's going to be 20 seconds
so the time it takes to make one
complete cycle is 20 seconds
the frequency
is 1 divided by the period
so it's going to be 1 over 20.
so 1 over 20 will give us a frequency
of 0.05 hertz
and so that's the answer for this
problem
so here's another example
go ahead and calculate the amplitude of
this particular mechanical wave
to calculate the amplitude
it's going to be the difference
between the highest value
and the lowest value divided by 2. so
let's say h is the highest value
l is the lowest value
and so it's going to be 12 minus 4
divided by 2. 12 minus 4 is 8 8 divided
by 2 is 4.
so the amplitude in this example is 4
meters
now the midpoint between 4 and 12 is 8.
if you add 12 plus 4 you get 16 divided
by 2 that's eight
and as you mentioned before the
amplitude
is the distance between the center line
and the highest point
so 12 minus eight is four and that will
give us
the same answer
now what is the period
of this particular wave
so notice that the six seconds
corresponds to three-fourths
of a cycle
which would basically stop here at the
bottom
so if we divide it into three
six divided by three is two so
the quarter cycle would be at two
seconds
the half cycle would be at four
and so a full cycle would be 8 seconds
therefore the period is 8 seconds
and now we can calculate the frequency
so the frequency is 1 over the period so
that's 1 over 8 seconds
and 1 over 8
will give us a frequency of
0.125 hertz
and so that's how you can calculate the
amplitude the frequency the wavelength
and the period
of a mechanical wave represented by a
graph
number four
a mechanical wave moves in a string with
a speed of 125 meters per second
if the frequency of the wave is 250
hertz what is the wavelength
so how can we find the answer for this
problem
the speed of a wave is equal to the
wavelength times the frequency
and so the wave speed is 125 meters per
second
we're looking for the wavelength and the
frequency is 250 hertz
so to calculate the wavelength it's
simply the wave speed
divided by the frequency
so 125 divided by 250
is 0.5
so it's 0.5 meters
number five
a two meter long string with a mass of
0.10 kilograms is plucked with a tension
force
of 500 newtons
what is the linear density of the string
the linear density
is simply the mass per unit length
the mass of the string is 0.10 kilograms
and the string is 2 meters long
so 0.10 divided by 2
will give us a linear density of
kilograms per meter
now let's draw a picture so let's say if
we have two boundaries
and a string is in between them
if we apply a force
or tension force on the string
we can create a wave pattern on a string
and so you might get a wave
and
what we need to do in part b is
calculate how fast that wave is moving
if we pluck it with
a given tension force
the velocity of the wave
is equal to the square root
of the tension force
divided by the linear density
the mass per unit length
so in this example the tension force is
500 newtons
and the linear density is 0.05
so 500 divided by 0.05 that's 10 000. if
we take the square root of that that
will give us a speed of 100
meters per second
so that's the answer to part b
part c determine the frequency of the
wave if it has a wavelength of 0.25
meters
we know that the wave speed is the
wavelength times the frequency
so the frequency has to be the wave
speed divided by the wavelength so it's
going to be 100 meters per second
divided by a wavelength of 0.25 meters
and so that's going to give us a
frequency
of 400 hertz
and that's the answer to part c
number six
a standard wave is moving at 130 meters
per second on a 2.5 meter long string
what is the fundamental frequency of
this wave feel free to try if you want
to
to calculate the fundamental frequency
you can use this equation
it's nv
over 2l
now n is one when dealing with the
fundamental frequency
so it's going to be 1 times the wave
speed which is 130 meters per second
and the length of the string is 2.5
meters
so 2 times 2.5 is 5
so it's 130 over 5.
so the fundamental frequency
is 26 hertz
so that's the answer to part a
now part b
what is the frequency of the third
harmonic
that's going to be f3
the frequency of the third harmonic is
simply three times the fundamental
frequency the fundamental frequency
being f1 the second harmonic is f2 the
third harmonic f3 fourth harmonic f4 and
so forth
so the third harmonic is simply three
times the fundamental frequency
or three times 26
which is 78 hertz
now let's move on to part c
how many nodes and antinodes are present
in the third
in the wave of the third harmonic
so the first harmonic looks like this
so that's f1
the second harmonic
looks like that that's f2
the third harmonic
let me draw that better
that's the third harmonic
so
these are the nodes the third harmonic
has four nodes
the antinodes
are where you have the maximum
displacement
or that's where constructive
interference occurs
so there's three anti-nodes
the nodes occur with destructive
interference that's when the amplitude
is zero
so the number of nodes
is equal to n plus one
and the number of antinodes
is equal to n
so for the third harmonic n is three
notice that the antinodes in n are the
same
and the number of nodes is four it's n
plus one so if we're dealing with the
seventh harmonic
the number of nodes
is going to be seven plus one it's gonna
be eight the number of antinodes which
i'm going to know a n that's gonna be
seven
now let's move on to part d
what is the frequency of the fifth
overtone
you need to know that the first overtone
i'm just going to put ot for overtone
the first overtone corresponds to the
second harmonic
the second overtone
corresponds to the third harmonic
so the fifth overtone
corresponds to the sixth harmonic
the frequency of the six harmonic
is going to be six times the fundamental
frequency
or six times 26 hertz
and so it's going to be 156 hertz so
that's the frequency of the fifth
overtone
which is the sixth harmonic
now what is the wavelength of the third
overtone
so the third overtone
represents the fourth harmonic
so the formula that we can use
to calculate
the wavelength of the fourth harmonic is
this equation
it's going to be 2l over n
so it's twice the length of the string
two times two point five
divided by four
so it's five over four
so the wavelength of the
fourth harmonic or the third overtone
is 1.25 meters
now there's another way in which we can
calculate it
so we could find
the frequency of the four harmonic which
is going to be four times 26
and that's 104 hertz
and then we could use this equation
the speed is the wavelength times the
frequency so the wavelength
that is the
the wavelength for the fourth harmonic
is going to be the speed
divided by the frequency of the four
harmonic
so the speed is 130
and the frequency of the fourth harmonic
is 104 hertz
so if you take 130 and divided by 104
it will give you the same answer of 1.25
meters
and so that's it for this video
you